<page title="Windows">
	<h2>Windows</h2>
	<p>Download <download prefix="asap-" suffix="-win32.msi" />.
	It's an installer for Windows 11/10/8/7/Vista/XP, also the 64-bit ones.</p>

	<h2>foobar2000</h2>
	<p><a href="https://www.foobar2000.org/">foobar2000</a> is the recommended player.
	The ASAP installer detects it and installs a suitable plugin.
	If you want to install just the foobar2000 plugin and nothing else, there's an alternative download:
	<download prefix="foo_asap-" suffix=".fb2k-component" />.</p>
	<p>foobar2000 can play directly from ZIP files, so you don't even need to unpack them. The plugin also supports ATR disk images.
	You can also convert, e.g. to MP3.</p>
	<p>To view and edit metadata, select "View/ASAP info". This doesn't work inside ZIP archives.</p>
	<img src="foobar2000.png" alt="foobar2000" />

	<h2>XMPlay</h2>
	<p><a href="https://www.un4seen.com/xmplay.html">XMPlay</a> is a player supporting MOD and similar formats out of the box.
	The ASAP plugin can display RMT instrument names. If you want to use the "File information" window
	(to edit tags or convert between SAP and other formats), assign a shortcut to it from within XMPlay options.</p>
	<img src="xmplay.png" alt="XMPlay" />

	<h2>Winamp</h2>
	<p><a href="https://www.winamp.com/">Winamp</a> is a pure old-school classic! Believe it or not, it does work on Windows 10.
	The ASAP plugin supports ATR disk images.</p>
	<img src="winamp.png" alt="Winamp" />

	<h2>BASS / AIMP</h2>
	<p><a href="https://www.un4seen.com/bass.html">BASS</a> is a component that provides audio playback
	in <a href="https://www.aimp.ru/">AIMP</a> and <a href="https://www.un4seen.com/bass_showcase.php">other players</a>.
	The ASAP installer detects AIMP. For other players, modify the install directory.</p>
	<p>For 64-bit AIMP, you need to install <download prefix="asap-" suffix="-win64.msi" />.
	It is okay to have both 32-bit and 64-bit ASAP packages installed at the same time.</p>
	<img src="aimp.png" alt="AIMP" />

	<h2>VLC</h2>
	<p><a href="https://www.videolan.org/vlc/">VLC</a> is a popular video player that plays audio as well.
	It provides limited support for the SAP file format out of the box (no digitized sounds, buggy emulation).
	For best experience, install the ASAP plugin.</p>
	<p>For 64-bit VLC, you need to install <download prefix="asap-" suffix="-win64.msi" />.</p>
	<img src="vlc.png" alt="VLC" />

	<h2>Raster Music Tracker</h2>
	<p><a href="http://raster.infos.cz/atari/rmt/rmt.htm">RMT</a> is a chiptune editor running on Windows.
	For better emulation of the POKEY chip, install the ASAP plugin.</p>

	<h2>WASAP</h2>
	<p>WASAP is a tiny standalone player. When you run it, an "Open file" dialog appears.
	Simply select the file you want to listen to. WASAP is later controlled by its red tray icon.
	When you hover the mouse pointer over the icon, the name of the loaded file appears.
	To open another file, left-click the tray icon. The other options are
	available in the menu which appears when you right-click the icon.</p>
	<p>Because of limited functionality of WASAP (for instance, no playlist),
	it's recommended to use the previously described players instead.</p>
	<img src="wasap.png" alt="WASAP" />

	<h2>Windows Explorer</h2>
	<p>The Windows Explorer extension provides no playback, only metadata display and editor.
	On 64-bit Windows, you need to install <download prefix="asap-" suffix="-win64.msi" />.</p>
	<img src="shellex.png" alt="Windows Explorer" />

	<h2>asapconv</h2>
	<p>For command-line conversions (e.g. to WAV or between SAP and the tracker formats)
	and editing the metadata, use asapconv. Run the program from the command prompt to see the syntax.
	The <code>-o/--output</code> option selects the output format and is mandatory.</p>

	<h2>Manual installation</h2>
	<p>If you are allergic to installers, download <download prefix="asap-" suffix="-win32.zip" />
	and extract the files to proper locations.</p>
</page>
